Leach, W. Barton (Walter Barton), 1900 -1971. Papers, 1920-1971: Finding Aid.
Papers, 1920-1971.
- CONTINGENT I
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (UNBOUND)
    - W-Miscellany (alphabetical), 11-22 to 11-23
      - 11-22, Wadsworth, Charles Y. 1960-1967 Wagner, Jerry 1968 Wailes, Esme 1963-1966 Wallace, Warrack 1957 Wallenfels, Helmut 1962 Walter, Stephen 1968 Ware, Lindsay 1967 Watkins, Arthur 1958-1960 Watts, David A. 1961 Watts, William 1960 Webster, James A., Jr. 1964-1966 Weidner, E. Merritt 1959 Weiss, J.A. 1958 Wesselhoeft, William H. 1966 Westmoreland, W.C. (Major General,; West Point) 1962 Wheeler, Henry 3rd, 1962-1963 Wheeless, Leon L. 1959
      - 11-23, Whelpley, Richard 1970-1971 Whitby, Roger M. 1968 White, Edward S. 1970 White, Thomas D. 1961-1965 Whitehead, Donald D. 1969 Whitehead, Whitney 1968 Whitman, Esther C. 1969 Wides, Burton 1961 Wigan, Audrey 1965 Williams, David Howard 1964 Williams, Howard R. 1969 Wilmeth, Philip 1965 Wilson, John P. 1967 Wiseley, William 1963 Wohlstetter, Alberta 1962 Wolf, Jerome T. 1962 Woodbury, Peter 1959 Woodhouse, Thomas Edwin 1968 World Publishing Company 1958 Woodworth, Anthony J. 1964 Woodworth, Ralph 1965 Wyatt, Joseph L., Jr. 1963 Wylie, John S. 1967
    - XYZ-Miscellany (alphabetical), 11-24
      The Yale Law Journal 1963
      Yale University Law School 1962-1967
      Yale University Press 1971
      Young, Harold W. 1969
      Youngs, Eugene W. 1969
      Zimmerman, Carroll L. 1962
      Zuckert, Eugene M. 1961
    - Unidentified, 11-25
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (BOUND)
    This is a so-called "dictation file" of carbons of letters sent out by WBL. Carbons were bound in chronological order, each volume covering six months of a given year. The period covered is January 1, 1958 to December 31, 1970. In content, the series is similar to the unbound correspondence series.
    - January 1, 1958 to December 31, 1958, 12-1
    - January 1, 1959 to June 30, 1959, 12-2
    - July 1, 1959 to December 31, 1959, 13-1
    - January 1, 1960 to June 30, 1960, 13-2
    - July, 1960 to December 31, 1960, 13-3
    - January 1, 1961 to June 30, 1961, 14-1
    - July 1, 1961 to December 31, 1961, 14-2
    - January 1, 1962 to June 30, 1962, 14-3
    - July 1, 1962 to December 31, 1962, 15-1
    - January 1, 1963 to December 31, 1963, 15-2
    - January 1, 1964 to December 31, 1964, 15-3
    - January 1, 1965 to December 31, 1965, 16-1
    - January 1, 1966 to December 31, 1966, 16-2
    - January 1, 1967 to September 30, 1967, 17-1
    - October 1, 1967 to December 31, 1967, 17-2
    - January 1, 1968 to December 31, 1968, 17-3
    - January 1, 1969 to December 31, 1969, 18-1
    - January 1, 1970 to December 31, 1970, 18-2
  - TEACHING NOTES
    This Series relates primarily to courses on Property (conveyancing, wills, future interests, perpetuities) with some material on Evidence and Contracts. Boxes 19 to 24 contain looseleaf books filled with notes and assignments. Boxes 25 and 26 contain unbound notes, correspondence with students and material for a manual (never published) for law students.
    - Contracts (undated) 3 folders, 19-1 to 19-3
    - Evidence (undated), 20-1
    - Property I (undated) 3 folders, 20-2 to 21-1
    - Property II 1932-1933, 21-2
    - Property II 1951, 21-3
    - Property II 1952, 22-1
    - Property II (undated) 4 folders, 22-2 to 23-2
    - Property III 1948, 24-1
    - Property III (undated) 2 folders, 24-2 to 24-3
    - Advisees, 25-1
      File relates to 1L students who were WBL's advisees during spring semester 1968.
    - Correspondence With Students 1964-1969 2 folders, 25-2 to 25-3
    - Future Interests and Estate Planning, 25-4
      File contains notes, correspondence, grade sheets, examination questions and communications from WBL to his classes.
    - L.L.B.-Manual for Law Students 10 folders, 25-5 to 26-5
      File relates to proposed book by WBL on legal education which was never written.
      25-5 to 25-7 contain correspondence.
      25-8 to 26-2 contain notes, memoranda, newspaper articles and other articles bearing on legal education.
      26-3 to 26-5 contain transcripts of speeches made at the Second Annual School for Young Lawyers, Harvard Law School Forum, November 10,11, 1949.
    - Property I 4 folders, 26-6 to 26-9
      File contains notes, correspondence, grade sheets, examination questions and various communications from WBL to his classes.
    - Student Memos
      See: WRITINGS AND RESEARCH: Zimmerman v. Shreeve
    - Teaching Miscellany, 26-10
  - WRITINGS AND RESEARCH
    This Series relates to books, articles and speeches by WBL and to material on perpetuity reform throughout the world. It consists of notes, drafts, research material, final typewritten manuscripts and reprints of some of WBL's writings and speeches as well as correspondence about specific subjects or specific pieces of writing. A substantial part of this Series deals with the three casebooks (on wills, property and future interests) put together by WBL, alone or in conjunction with others.
    This Series begins with books by WBL, arranged alphabetically by author or co-author. Speeches and articles are then arranged chronologically by date of publication or delivery. Research material on perpetuities reform is at the end, arranged alphabetically.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 1st Edition, Little, Brown Company, 1950, Correspondence, 27-1
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 1st Edition, Notes, 27-2 to 27-3
      File contains memoranda, newspaper articles and summaries of cases; also a copy in 27-3 of the 1964 Supplement for Chapter 17.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Little, Brown Company, 1969, Correspondence 1962-1969, 27-4 to 27-5
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Notes, 27-6 to 27-8
      File contains suggestions from contributors to the 1st Edition, rough notes, communications between Casner and WBL. 27-7 contains a copy of the proceedings of the ABA Section of Real Property Probate and Trust Law in San Francisco, August 6,7, 1962.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, 27-9
      Corrections of Misprints
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Preface, 27-10
      File contains xerox copy of first draft of the Preface.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part I, 27-11
      File contains a note from C.A. Peairs, Jr., 1950.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part II, Chapters 2,3, 27-12
      File contains notes, Congressional bills and a letter from Senator Pat McCarran of Nevada on the Pyramid Lake Indian Reservation dispute. Also contains pamphlet "Improving the Lot of the Trespassing Improver" by John Henry Merryman.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part II-Chapter 4, 27-13
      File contains background material.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part II-Chapters 5,6,7,8, 27-14
      File contains notes and background material.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part III-Chapters 9,10,11, 27-15
      File contains notes, background material and carbon copies of drafts for parts of these chapters.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part IV-Chapter 12, Introduction, 27-16
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part IV-Chapter 12, 27-17
      File includes a copy of "The Tenentry on the New York Manors" by Arthur E. Sutherland. Contains notes and other background material.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part IV-Chapters 13, 14, 27-18
      File contains notes and background materials.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part V-Chapter 15, 27-19
      Contains carbon draft of revision of part of Chapter 15.
    - Casner and Leach, Casea and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part V-Chapter 16, Section 2, 27-20
      File contains 1960 student note relating the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle to Chapter 16.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part V-Chapter 16 3 folders, 28-1 to 28-3
      File is labelled as Section 8 of Chapter 16. In the 2nd edition, however, there is no Section 8. File relates mostly to the development of land law in England and the United States. It contains notes, newspaper articles and a paper for Property III (1949-1950) by Arthur S.W. Chantry entitled "The Development of Land Law in America".
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VI-Chapters 17,19,20,23, 28-4
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Introduction, 28-5
      File contains a copy of "The Drafting of Percentage Leases" by Henry Landis, reprinted from The University of Toronto Law Journal, No. 1, 1955.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, PartVII-Chapter 24, 28-6
      File contains notes, drafts for the chapter and teaching material from Professor Francis A. Allen; (Harvard Law School).
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Chapters 25,26, 28-7
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Chapter 28, 28-8
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Chapter 29, Introduction, 28-9
      File contains sketches of cases.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Chapter 29, 28-10 to 28-11
      File contains notes, correspondence and a pamphlet, "American Land Law Reform: Modernization of Recording Statutes (Part I)" by Robert N. Cook assisted by Frederick M. Lombardi.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VII-Chapters 30,31, 28-12
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VIII-Chapters 32,33, 28-13
      File contains notes, background material, and a pamphlet "Regionalism and Realism in Land-Use Planning" by Charles M. Haar.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VIII-Chapter 34, 28-14
      File contains pamphlet "Reverters, Rights of Entry, and Executory Interests: Semantic Confusion and the Tying Up of Land" by Verner F. Chaffin.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Part VIII-Chapter 35, 28-15
      File is labelled Chapter 38, but it relates to material listed under Chapter 35 of the casebook (2nd edition); there is no Chapter 38 in the 2nd edition.
    - Casner and Leach, Cases and Text on Property, 2nd Edition, Teachers' Manual, 28-16
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, Little, Brown Company, 1947, Correspondence, 29-1 to 29-2
      File includes a review of the book in the May, 1948 issue of the University of Pennsylvania Law Review; a copy of "General Form Of Will With Trust Provisions", prepared by the Marine Midland Trust Company, 1949; and teaching materials sent by Professor W.D. MacDonald of the University of Florida, College of Law, 1951.
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, Suggestions for Teachers, 29-3
      File contains correspondence.
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, 1955 Revision, 29-4
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, 1960 Revision, Correspondence, 29-5
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, 1960 Revision, Notes and Drafts, 29-6 to 29-7
      File contains carbon copies of drafts for several parts of the revised casebook.
    - Leach, Cases and Text on the Law of Wills, 2nd Edition, Possible Revisions, 29-8
      File contains correspondence (1964-1969) re possible changes in the 1960 revision of the 2nd Edition and raising the possibility of a 3rd Edition.
    - Leach and Liacos, Handbook of Massachusetts Evidence, 4th Edition, Little, Brown Company, 1967, 29-9
      File contains correspondence re the revision of the Handbook by Professor Paul J. Liacos.
    - Leach, Cases and Materials on the Law of Future Interests, Foundation Press, 2nd Edition, 1950, 29-10
      File contains correspondence with the Foundation Press.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Foundation Press 1961, Correspondence, 29-11 to 29-14
      This book was the successor to Leach, Cases and Materials on the Law of Future Interests. File contains correspondence between WBL and the Foundation Press and between WBL and Professor Logan. See also GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (UNBOUND): Logan, James K.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Notes and Citations, 30-1 to 30-2
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Part IV, Chapter 21, 30-3
      File relates to "Advocacy Technique in the Rockies", pp. 710-712; material is dated 1952-1953.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Part IV, Chapter 23, Sears Vs. Coolidge, 30-4 to 30-5
      File contains correspondence, notes and several drafts for section of the casebook involved.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, 1962 Supplement, 30-6
      File contains a copy of the Supplement.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Teacher's Manual, 30-7
      File contains notes, correspondence, a copy of the Manual and a copy of the 1962 Supplement to the Manual.
    - Leach and Logan, Cases and Text on Future Interests and Estate Planning, Materials Re Possible 2nd Edition, 30-8 to 30-9
      File contains mostly notes with some correspondence.
    - Leach and Morris, The Rule Against Perpetuities, 1st Edition, Stevens Sons Limited, 1956, 30-10
      File contains correspondence and a reprint of a review of the book by Cecil A. Wright (Dean,; Faculty of Law, University of Toronto) in the Canadian Bar Review, 1956. The 2nd Edition of Leach and Morris appeared in 1962. J.H.C. Morris was Professor of Law, Oxford University, England.
    - Leach and Tudor, The Rule Against Perpetuities, Little, Brown Company, 1957, 30-11 to 30-12
      File relates to work by WBL and Mr. Owen Tudor which was Part 24 of the American Law of Property.
      30-11 contains correspondence re Leach and Tudor and re its 1962 Supplement. Under September 22, 1958 there is a reprint of a review of the book in the Washington University Law Quarterly by John E. Howe (Professor of Law,; St. Louis University). There are also carbon drafts of various sections of the work and proof sheets of Parts 23 and 24 of ALP.
      30-12 contains proof sheets and carbon drafts. For other proof sheets see WRITINGS AND RESEARCH: Carter v. Berry.
    - Leach, Harvard Law: Memorabilia and Curiosa, 30-13 to 31-10
      File relates to projected work of WBL for Little, Brown Company which was never completed.
    - Solicitations (alphabetical) 1957-1969, 31-11 to 31-12
      File relates to invitations to WBL to publish articles or to review books in various law reviews.
      - 31-11, Catholic University Law Review 1968 Columbia Law Review 1967-1968 Denver Law Journal 1967 Duquesne University Law Review 1966 Fordham University Law Review 1961-1969 The Georgetown Law Journal 1966 Iowa Law Review 1959 Maine Law Review 1967-1968 Minnesota Law Review 1963-1969 Missouri Law Review 1966 New Hampshire Bar Association Journal 1961 New York Law Forum 1967 Northwestern University Law Review 1969 Notre Dame Lawyer1966 The Phoenix ( Queens College) 1966 Rutgers Law Review 1957-1969
      - 31-12, Stanford Law Review 1965 Suffolk University Law Review 1967 U.C.L.A. Law Review 1965-1968 University of Colorado Law Review 1967 University of Miami Law Center, Journal of Estate Planning 1967 University of Michigan Law Review 1960 University of Pittsburgh Law Review 1965 Vanderbilt Law Review 1968 Villanova Law Review 1964-1965 Virginia Law Review 1959-1962 Washington and Lee Law Review 1968 Wayne Law Review 1961
    - Speeches and Discussions (alphabetical) 1958-1960, 31-13
      File relates to talks and performances given by WBL and to discussion groups of which he was a member; file does not contain copies of his remarks.
      American Bar Association Meeting, Real Estate Section 1960
      Boston Safe Deposit and Trust Company 1959
      Boston University 1959-1960
      British Broadcasting Company 1958
      George Washington University 1958
      Institute of World Affairs, Inc. 1958
      Phillips Exeter Academy 1959
      Suffolk University Law School 1959
      United States Military Academy 1959
      United States Naval and Marine Corps Reserve Training Center, Boston 1959
    - " To Clear Courts of Auto Cases", Boston Evening Transcript, January 22, 1932, 32-1
      File relates to article by WBL on No-Fault insurance.
    - "Your Will and Your Family", Speech to Women's Community League of Weston, December 7, 1936, 32-2
    - "Folk Music of American Law Schools", Association of American Law Schools Smoker, December 30, 1936, 32-3
    - Speech at Annual Dinner of the American Law Institute, Washington, D.C., May 7, 1937, 32-4
    - "Constitution Day Speech", Delivered at Weston High School, September 17, 1937, 32-5
    - Lincoln's Inn Christmas Dinner Speech, December 15, 1937, 32-6
    - Leach editor, Langdell Lyrics of 1938, The Foundation Press, Inc., 1938, 32-7
      File contains a copy of the Lyrics.
    - "The Vocation and Avocation of a Law Professor", Speech to the Ohio State Bar Association, January 29, 1938, 32-8
    - "Perpetuities In A Nutshell", Harvard Law Review, February 1938, 32-9
    - Speech to Rhode Island Bar Association, Providence,March 22, 1938, 32-10
    - Speech to Annual Dinner of the American Law Institute, Washington, D.C., May 13, 1938, 32-11
    - "The Rule Against Perpetuities and Gifts to Classes", Harvard Law Review, June 1938, 32-12
    - "Powers of Appointment", American Bar Association Journal, October 1938, 32-13
      File contains a reprint of WBL's article and material re two speeches by WBL: to the Practicing Law Institute, September 29, 1941; and to the New England Trust Conference, December 12, 1941.
    - Speech at Wheeling Dollar Savings Trust Co. Dinner, November 21, 1938, 32-14
    - New Hampshire Bar Association Lecture, July 1, 1939, 32-15
    - Connecticut Bar Association Legal Institute Lecture, November 6, 1939, 32-16
    - Talk on Being a Holmes Secretary, WBZ Radio, November 9, 1939, 32-17
    - Indiana State Bar Association Legal Institute Lecture, January 12, 1940, 32-18
    - Speech at the Judge's Gavel Annual Banquet, Yale Law School, February 15, 1941, 32-19
    - Washoe County Bar Association Legal Institute Lectures, July 30, 31, August 1, 1941, 32-20
    - "Powers in Life Tenants to Consume Principal", Speech to Corporate Fiduciaries Association of Rhode Island, December 11, 1941, 32-21
    - Speech to " Forum on Legal Education", Yale Law School, December 4, 1946, 32-22
    - Book Review by WBL of Touched With Fire: Civil War Letters and Diary of Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr., Edited by Mark DeWolfe Howe, Yale Law Journal, January 1947, 32-23
      File contains two pages of a carbon copy of the review.
    - Agwam Hunt Club Entertainment, October 24, 1947, 32-24
    - "Law Teaching", Talk to Faculty, Northeastern Law School, October 30, 1947, 32-25
    - "Education in a Reconstructed World: Citizenship and Civil Liberties", Speech to Harvard Teachers Association, March 20, 1949, 32-26
    - "Wills, Trusts and Taxes", Speech to Women's Finance Forum, Worcester, Mass., May 1, 1950, 32-27
    - "Wills, Trusts and Taxes", Speech to Women's Finance Forum, Greenwich, Conn., June 12, 1950, 32-28
    - " Wills, Trusts and Taxes", Speech to Women's Finance Forum, New Haven, Conn., November 13, 1950, 32-29
    - " Trusts, Wills and Estates", Speech to Women's Finance Forum, Boston, Mass., March 19, 1951, 32-30
    - Speech at Yale Law Association Dinner, April 25, 1951, 32-31
    - "Wills, Trust and Taxes", Speech to Women's Financial Forum, Hartford, Conn., May 1, 1951, 32-32
    - "Perpetuities: Staying the Slaughter of the Innocents", The Law Quarterly Review, January 1952, 32-33
      File contains a reprint of WBL's article.
    - "Perpetuities in Perspective: Ending the Rule's Reign of Terror", Harvard Law Review, March 1952, 32-34
    - "A Proposed Statute", Proceedings of Probate and Trust Law Divisions, American Bar Association, August 24-26, 1953, Boston, Mass., 32-35
      File contains a reprint of the proceedings.
    - "Perpetuities Reform by Legislation", The Law Quarterly Review, October 1954, 32-36
      File contains correspondence, carbon drafts and a reprint of WBL's article.
    - "Remarks on Power and Policy", Speech at University of Pennsylvania, February 9, 1955, 32-37
    - "Perpetuities Reform by Legislation: England", Harvard Law Review, June 1957, 32-38
      File contains correspondence and proof sheets of WBL's article.
    - Book Review by WBL of The Memoirs of Field Marshal Montgomery, Air Force, November 1958, 33-1
      File contains two copies of the review, one from Air Force, the other from The Airman's Bookshelf, Autumn 1958.
    - "Method of Assuring Continuity of Civilian Leadership in the Pentagon", Speech to The Society of American Military Engineers, Boston Post, May 27, 1959, 33-2
      File contains correspondence and photograph of WBL; no copy of the speech.
    - Voice of America 1960, 33-3
      File contains script by WBL on private property.
    - Book Review by WBL of Introduction to the Law of Property, by F.H. Lawson, New York University Law Review, January 1960, 33-4
      File contains correspondence, a carbon copy and a reprint of the review.
    - "Perpetuities: New Absurdity, Judicial and Statutory Correctives", Harvard Law Review, May 1960, 33-5
      File contains correspondence and two drafts of WBL's article.
    - "Perpetuities Legislation: Hail Pennsylvania!", University of Pennsylvania Law Review, June 1960 5 folders, 33-6 to 33-10
      File contains correspondence, notes and background material; also comments on WBL's article and several drafts and a reprint of the article.
    - Book Review by WBL of The Improvement of Conveyancing by Legislation by Simes and Taylor, Michingan Law Review, June 1960, 33-11
    - "Perpetuities in Real Estate: Legislative Reform", The Practical Lawyer, December 1960, 33-12
      File relates to paper delivered by WBL to the 83rd Annual Meeting of the American Bar Association in summer 1960 (paper delivered under the title "Perpetuities: Let's Get the Rule on the Rails"). A slightly revised version was then published by The Practical Lawyer. File contains correspondence, drafts of the paper and a copy of the issue of The Practical Lawyer in which the article appears.
    - "The Careful Draftsman: Watch Out!", American Bar Association Journal, March 1961, 33-13
    - Speech to Cleveland Bar Association Annual Meeting, May 4, 1961, 33-14
      File contains correspondence; no copy of speech.
    - "Perpetuities in the Atomic Age: The Sperm Bank and the Fertile Decedent", American Bar Association Journal, October 1962, 33-15
    - "America's Social Frontiers: The Rights of the Frozen Heir", Current, December 1962, 33-16
    - "Perpetuities Reform: London Proposes, Perth Disposes", University of Western Australia Annual Law Review, 1963, 33-17
      File contains correspondence (1958-1968), much of it with Professor David Allan. While perpetuities reform is the subject of the correspondence, it does not all relate to the article. There are two drafts of the article in file.
    - "Perpetuities: Cy Pres on the March", Vanderbilt Law Review, October 1964, 33-18